<!DOCTYPE ui:UiBinder SYSTEM "http://dl.google.com/gwt/DTD/xhtml.ent">
<ui:UiBinder xmlns:ui="urn:ui:com.google.gwt.uibinder" xmlns:g="urn:import:com.google.gwt.user.client.ui">
  <ui:style>
    .manual {
      min-width: 500px;
    }

    .page {
      padding: 0px 15px 15px 15px;
    }

    .section {
      margin-bottom: 15px;
      border: 1px solid #81b0d4;
      border-collapse: separate;
      border-radius: 5px;
      overflow: hidden;
    }

    .section div {
      padding: 5px;
    }

    .header {
      font-weight: bold;
      padding-bottom: 7px;
      border-bottom: 1px solid #81b0d4;
      background: #e3eaef;
    }

    .manual ul {
      margin-top: 0.5em;
      padding-left: 25px;
    }

    .manual ul li {
      margin: 0 0 3px 0;
    }

    .manual h1 {
      font-size: 22px;
      color: #1d446b;
      margin-top: 20px;
      margin-bottom: 8px;
    }

    .manual h2 {
      font-size: 18px;
      color: #1d446b;
      margin-top: 20px;
      margin-bottom: 8px;
    }

    .manual h3 {
      font-size: 15px;
      color: #1d446b;
      margin-top: 14px;
      margin-bottom: 5px;
    }

    .manual p {
      text-align: justify;
      margin-top: 0px;
      margin-bottom: 10px;
    }
  </ui:style>

  <g:ScrollPanel>
    <g:HTML ui:field="aboutHTML" height="100%" width="100%" addStyleNames="{style.manual}">
      <div class="{style.page}">

        <h1>IDSM ChemWebRDF Manual</h1>
        The application is a part of the IDSM project and allows SPARQL querying of PubChem data.

        <h2>Data Schema</h2>
        <p>
          The database uses the data coming from the
          <a target="_blank" href="https://pubchemdocs.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/rdf">PubChemRDF</a> project that provides
          <a target="_blank" href="https://www.w3.org/TR/rdf11-primer/">RDF</a> formatted information available in the
          PubChem archive. It mainly comprises information from the PubChem Compound, Substance, and Bioassay databases.
        </p>

        <p>
          The PubChemRDF data includes many semantic relationships, for which existing ontologies are employed, whenever
          it is possible. Parts of these ontologies (e.g., class hierarchies, resource labels) are loaded into the
          database as well. Summarization of the used ontologies and relationship predicates are summarized in
          <a target="_blank" href="https://pubchemdocs.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/rdf$table1">the PubChemRDF documentation</a>.
        </p>

        Detail information can be found in the following documents:
        <ul>
          <li><a target="_blank" href="https://pubchemdocs.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/rdf">PubChemRDF</a> (project page)</li>
          <li><a target="_blank" href="ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubchem/presentations/pubchem_rdf_intro.pdf">PubChemRDF introduction</a> (slide presentation)</li>
          <li><a target="_blank" href="ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubchem/presentations/pubchem_rdf_details.pdf">PubChemRDF detail</a> (slide presentation)</li>
          <li><a target="_blank" href="ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubchem/presentations/pubchem_rdf_tutorial.pdf">PubChemRDF tutorial</a> (slide presentation)</li>
          <li><a target="_blank" href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26175801">PubChemRDF: towards the semantic annotation of PubChem compound and substance databases</a> (publication)</li>
        </ul>

        <h2>User Interface</h2>
        <p>
          The user interface of the application is divided into three parts. The left part contains a query editor that
          allows users to write SPARQL queries. The query result is visualized as a table in the central part of the
          application. And finally, the right part of the application is used to visualize details about the selected
          resource.
        </p>

        <h3>Query Editor</h3>
        <p>
          The query editor is based on the third-party <a target="_blank" href="https://codemirror.net/">CodeMirror</a>
          component. It highlights <a target="_blank" href="https://www.w3.org/TR/sparql11-query/">SPARQL</a> syntax,
          and supports auto-completion of predicates used in the PubChemRDF data. Namespace prefixes used by the
          PubChemRDF project are predefined in used SPARQL engine, so they do not have to be explicitly defined in a
          query.
        </p>

        <p>
          The users can write a whole SPARQL query from the beginning or they can load a predefined query which can be
          further modified. If the query is stored in a file, then the <i>Open</i> button allows the users to load the
          query into the editor. Another possibility is to select one of the predefined examples queries by clicking on
          the <i>Examples</i> button. These examples are adopted from
          <a target="_blank" href="https://pubchemdocs.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/rdf$_8">PubChemRDF use cases</a>. And finally,
          the third option is to use a wizard to generate a query.
        </p>

        <p>
          A prepared query can be submitted to the SPARQL engine for evaluation by clicking on the <i>Run</i> button.
          Alternatively, the query can be saved into the file for later use.
        </p>

        <h3>Query Wizard</h3>
        <p>
          The wizard allows the users to generate queries that search for compounds, bioassays, participants (proteins
          or genes) or their combinations. If the compound search and the bioassay search are both enabled, then the
          generated query searches only for the compounds that were tested in the searched bioassays. Similarly, if the
          bioassay search and the participant search are both enabled, then the query searches only for bioassays having
          the given participants.
        </p>

        The following search criteria can be set:
        <ul>
          <li><i>Compound search:</i> If a molecule structure (in SMILES or the Molfile format) is provided, then the wizard generates a query that employs the <a target="_blank" href="https://jcheminf.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13321-019-0367-2">Sachem</a> compound search. Substructure, exact, or similarity compound search are supported.</li>
          <li><i>Bioassay search:</i> Bioassays can be searched according to keywords (if provided) included in their names or descriptions. Keywords are specified in <a target="_blank" href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/12/textsearch-controls.html#TEXTSEARCH-PARSING-QUERIES">the PostgreSQL full-text query syntax</a>. If the compound search is also enabled, then requested result statuses of compounds in searched bioassays can be specified.</li>
          <li><i>Participant search:</i> Participants are searched according to their names (the PostgreSQL full-text query syntax is used) or according to their types (gene or protein).</li>
        </ul>

        <p>
          Finally, the wizard allows specifying which kinds of searched entities should be included in the final result.
          It is also possible to specify the requested ordering of the result.
        </p>

        <p>
          Please note that queries generated by the wizard are not submitted automatically and have to be also submitted
          by clicking on the <i>Run</i> button.
        </p>

        <h3>Result Presentation</h3>
        <p>
          The result of a submitted query is shown as the table in the central part of the application interface. Each
          variable used in the select clause of the query is represented by one column. Individual solution mapping
          forming single results are represented by rows. Only the first thousand solution mappings (i.e., rows) are
          shown. Other solutions can be showed by using the pagination navigation buttons located at the bottom of the
          result table. The showed solutions can be filtered by the filter box on the top of the result table. The
          filtration criteria can be restricted only to contents of a selected variable.
        </p>

        <p>
          If the value to which a variable is bound is an IRI identifying a resource of a supported type, then the
          appropriate <i>item template</i> is used to visualize the appropriate table cell. Otherwise, the value itself
          is used as the cell content. The visualisation typically contains the label of the resource, that is
          separately searched for the given resource in the database.
        </p>

        <p>
          The <i>Details</i> tab located at the right part of the application is used to visualize details about the
          selected resource. The IRI of the resource can be entered directly by the address bar, or the resource can be
          selected from the result table. If details about the supported resource are requested, the application uses
          the appropriate <i>page template</i> to generate details about the resource.
        </p>

        <p>
          The Properties tab can be used to display all relations between selected resource and other resources or
          values. It uses the given resource as a subject and shows all predicates (properties) and objects (values) for
          which triples subject-predicate-object are stored in the database.
         </p>

        <h2>Program Interface</h2>
        <p>
          The web application is intended to be used only as a user interface. If it is required to use the database
          from other programs, for example as part as federated queries, the SPARQL endpoint
          https://idsm.elixir-czech.cz/sparql/endpoint/idsm should be used.
        </p>

      </div>
    </g:HTML>
  </g:ScrollPanel>
</ui:UiBinder>
